A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Business Records, 1789-1908
Library of Virginia
- Tannehill & Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874, 1 volume
  Scope and Content: Tannehill and Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874, records the accounts of individual customers and employees. Each account lists transactions in chronological order. Each entry for customer accounts includes the date, type of transaction, items purchased, quantity of items purchased, monies credited and debited, and method of payment. Customer accounts include transactions such as purchasing plants, hauling fertilizer, and planting trees. Plants purchased include ceder hedges, shade trees, standard pears and evergreens.
  Also included in the ledger are account records for the nursery's business operations and its employees. Business accounts document expenses like employee wages and purchases of inventory and equipment. Employee accounts record the labor performed by the worker such as planting trees, hauling wood, and plowing in addition to recording items purchased for the employee such as food, clothing, and tobacco. The majority of the nursery's employees were described as "colored."
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Franklin Davis vs Joseph F. Tannehill 1896-093. Avaible Digitially through Chancery Records Index.
  - Tannehill & Wheat Nursery Ledger, 1866-1874
- Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Henry I. Tapp was a lawyer in Staunton, Virginia, in the early nineteenth century until his death in 1830. Tapp was also involved in the building of the Staunton turnpike.
  Scope and Content: Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831, documents the financial activities of Tapp's law firm on an almost daily basis. Information found in the daybook entries include the name of client and the amounts owed or paid. Each entry can be found under the client's individual account in the ledger located at the back of the volume. Examples of the services provided by Tapp include serving as administrator and guardian, drafting deeds, taking depositions, settling estates, and arguing cases at court. The law firms expenses (such as travel, hire of horses, and purchasing wood) are also recorded in the daybook and ledger.
  Several entries also record the hiring out of Michael, Tom, Mike, and Dick, Black men enslaved by Tapp, for short durations for whitewashing, helping with a harvest, etc.
  Transactions entered in 1831 were made by Thomas J. Michie, another lawyer in Augusta County, who took over Tapp's cases after his death in 1830.
  - Henry I. Tapp Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1831
- Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1856-1860, 2 volumes
  Historical Information: Templeton and Company was a general store that operated in Summerdean, Virginia, from 1856 to 1858. John Wilson, Samuel M. Templeton, and John W. McCormack formed the partnership for the mercantile business in 1856, but by April 1858 the company had dissolved and disposed of its stock of goods at auction.
  Scope and Content: Templeton and Company Daybook and Ledger, 1826-1860 consists of a Daybook, 1856-1860 and Ledger, 1856-1860
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, John Wilson vs Samuel M. Templeton, 1870-089. Avaible Digitially through Chancery Records Index.
  - Templeton & Co. Daybook, 1856-1860
    Templeton and Company Daybook, 1856-1860, records the business transactions of the general store on a daily basis as they occurred. Information found in each entry includes the date, the name of the customer, the form of transaction, and the amount of monies debited and credited to the account. Each transaction was also recorded under the customer's name in the corresponding ledger. Templeton and Company sold a variety of items including tobacco, nails, sugar, cloth, coffee, tea, bacon, tea kettles, eggs, candles, clothing, stoneware, shoes, and produce. Records of sales begin in August of 1856 and continue through March of 1858. Beginning in late March of 1858, the daybook was used to document money received for the sale of the company's stock at auction. Each entry lists the name and amounts of the items sold and the money received for the sale. The back of the daybook contains a record for the grain (wheat, corn, rye, and oats) stored in Summerdean Mills for 1857 and 1858. The daybook also contains a record of unidentified payments made by Samuel M. Templeton in 1860 to various individuals.
  - Templeton & Co. Ledger, 1856-1860
    Ledger, 1856-1860, records the accounts of individual customers. Each customer account, recorded from 1856-1858, includes separate entries for purchases and payments made. Purchases were not detailed but rather include the notation "to merchandise," amounts purchased, price per unit, and the total purchase made for that day. However, details were provided for the payments made toward account balances. Templeton and Company accepted cash, bartered items (hides, soap, butter, bacon, apples, horses, buggies), and labor (hauling, chopping, work at store) as payments. The back of the volume includes entries pertaining to the dissolution of the business from 1858 to 1860. Information provided includes a listing of customers with outstanding balances and a listing of money collected by A. B. Lightner on behalf of Templeton and Company.
- Thornburg and Shafer Daybook 1877-1879, 1 volume
  Historical Information: Thornburg and Shafer was a livery and exchange stable located on New Street in Staunton, Virginia. The partnership originated between Thomas A. Shafer and Samuel T. Thornburg, the managing partner. On 15 July 1878, Levi Shafer purchased Thomas A. Shafer's share in the partnership. At the height of their business, the livery stable owned twenty horses, five carriages, ten buggies, and a number of wagons. The partnership was officially dissolved in 1883 by a decree rendered in the Augusta County chancery court.
  Scope and Content: Thornburg and Shafer Daybook, 1877-1879, records the daily activities of the Augusta County livery stable with transactions recorded on a chronological basis as they occurred. The daybook was used primarily to document customer transactions but a few company expenses were also recorded. Information found in each entry include the date, customer name, service purchased, and the monies debited or credited to their accounts. Customers made payments for the hire of saddle horses, wagons, and buggies. Livery fees were also recorded and include payments for board, feed, and shoeing. Company expenses recorded include rent and purchases of feed, coal, and wood.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Levi Shafer and Thomas A. Shafer vs S. T. Thornburg, 1870-089. Avaible Digitially through Chancery Records Index.
  - Thornburg and Shafer Daybook,1877-1879
- Unidentified General Store Daybooks 1828-1835, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: A dealer in dry-goods, groceries, and hardware, this unidentified general store operated in Staunton, Virginia, during the mid-nineteenth century.
  Scope and Content: Unidentified General Store Daybooks, 1828-1835, record business transactions as they occurred on an almost daily basis. Transactions were entered almost daily for 1828 through 1830, but entries became less frequent for the years 1831 through 1835. Information found in each entry includes the date, name of customer, name and quantity of goods purchased, form of payment, and amount owed. Examples of items purchased include books, sugar, coffee, tools, saddlery, cloth, paper, clothing, shoes, tobacco, tea, and whiskey.
  - Unidentified General Store Day Book, 1828
  - Unidentified General Store Day Book, 1829
  - Unidentified General Store Day Book,1830-1835
- Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873, 1 volume
  Historical Information: This unidentified grocer operated in the Augusta County, Virginia, area during the nineteenth century.
  Scope and Content: Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873, records financial activities on an almost daily basis. The volume was used primarily as a daybook to document customer purchases. Information found in each entry includes name of customer, name and quantity of goods purchased, and the monies debited or credited to the account. Examples of items sold include tobacco, whiskey, pickles, sugar, oysters, coffee, cigars, cherries, chickens, bacon, peaches, etc. Occasionally, throughout the volume, individual customer accounts were compiled. Such entries noted items purchased and payments made to the account. The grocer accepted cash as well as barter for payment.
  In addition, the account book was frequently used to document the cash on hand. Business as well as the personal expenses of the grocer owner were recorded in the account book. Business expenses included such items as rent, bar fixtures, hardware, and purchasing stock for the store. Paying for horses, livestock feed, wallpaper, as well as money loans were included among the private expenses of the business owner.
  - Unidentified Grocer Account Book, 1873
- Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875, 6 volumes
  Historical Information: The Virginia Banking and Trust Company was originally incorporated as the Virginia Insurance Company by an act of the General Assembly of Virginia passed 13 December 1865. Operating out of its headquarters in Staunton, Virginia, the company insured buildings, furniture, and other property against loss or damage by fire. The company also provided life insurance.
  Another act of the General Assembly of Virginia, passed 13 January 1871, changed the name of the company to the Virginia Banking and Trust Company. The company operated under this name until it was dissolved and sold its properties in October of 1875.
  Scope and Content: Virginia Banking and Trust Company Business Records, 1866-1875, consist of one cashbook, 1875, daybook,1873-1874; ledgers, 1866-1875; minute book, 1866-1875; and statement book, 1866-1875
  - Virginia Banking and Trust Company Cashbook No. 7,1875-1876
    The Virginia Banking and Trust Company Cashbook No. 7, 1875, records the financial activities of the company with transactions listed chronologically as they occurred. Entries document monies credited and debited for such activities as bills received, deposits by stockholders and insurance policy holders, interest on accounts, and company expenses for such items as office equipment, postage, attorney fees, and taxes. Accounts were balanced at the end of each day's entries and provide a profit and loss statement for that day's activities.
    Stored in the back of Cashbook No.7 are loose papers that contain a statement of policies issued or renewed in 1869 recorded by John C. Whitner an agent working in Atlanta, Georgia. Each entry includes the name of the insured, number of policies and renewals purchased, date of commencement of risk, insurance term, expiration of risk, amount insured, insurance rate, amount of premium, and a brief description of the policy and items insured. Items insured include law libraries, businesses and their stock of goods, and dwelling houses.
  - Virginia Banking and Trust Company Daybook, No. 6,1873-1874
    Virginia Banking and Trust Company Daybook No. 6, 1873-1874, documents business activities on a chronological basis as they occurred. Entries include the date, type of transaction, and monies debited and credited. Transactions recorded include purchases of insurance policies and company stock, bills receivable, and company expenses. Each day's entries were balanced and include the total amounts of monies on-hand in currency, gold, and checks.
  - Virginia Insurance Company General Ledger No. 1,1866-1875
    The Virginia Life Insurance Company General Ledger No. 1, 1866-1875, records various accounts that document the financial transactions of the company. Examples of accounts documented include capital stock, expenses, profits and losses, bills receivable, bills payable, and insurance premiums paid. Each entry includes the date, type of transactions, and the monies debited or credited to the various accounts.
  - Virginia Insurance Company Individual Ledger No. 1, 1866-1872
    The Virginia Life Insurance Company Individual Ledger No. 1, 1866-1875, provides a record of customer and employee accounts. The accounts of individual customers record the number of policies purchased or renewed; although, no information is provided as to what the policies insured. Information found in the customer accounts include the amounts paid toward insurance policies and to whom the payments were made. The ledger was also used to record the accounts of company employees and insurance agents. Information found under employee accounts include the number of policies sold, the amount of monies collected for insurance payments, and amounts paid for expenses such as postage, travel, taxes, and attorney fees.
  - Virginia Insurance Company Minute Book, 1866-1875
    The Virginia Life Insurance Minute Book, 1866-1875, records the minutes for the meetings of the board of directors in addition to recording stockholder meetings. The minutes detail the business of selling stock and acquiring stockholders. Information on creating insurance policies and preparing insurance rates are provided. Meeting minutes also provide detail on policy applications, which describe the items and amounts insured. Also included in the volume are the by-laws created by the company.
  - Virginia Insurance Company Statement Book No. 1,1866-1875
    The Virginia Life Insurance Statement Book, 1866-1875, is a balance sheet that describes the total assets, liabilities and net worth of the business. Entries were made on a monthly basis and document stock investments, bills receivable, monies due, commissions, cash on hand, and estimated profits.
- Virginia Express Company Minute Book and Cashbook, 1867-1869, 3 volumes
  Historical Information: The Virginia Express Company, incorporated by an act of the General Assembly on 23 February 1867, was a freight and cargo transport company operating out of Staunton, Virginia. The company used both stage lines and railroads to ship its freight. During the establishment of the company, Michael G. Harman served as president and William Watts was a clerk for the company. In December 1868, the Virginia Express Company relinquished control of its shipping lines. The stage line business was taken over by Trotter & Company and Harman & Company, while the railroad interests were taken over by the Adams Express and Southern Express Companies.
  Scope and Content: Virginia Express Company Minute Books and Cashbook, 1867-1869, consists of a cashbook, 1867-1869, and minute books, 1867-1869.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, Norfolk and Petersburg Railroad Company vs Virginia Express Company, 1891-077. Avaible Digitially through Chancery Records Index.
  - Virginia Express Company Cash Book,1867-1869
    The Virginia Express Company Cashbook, 1867-1869, records the cash received and cash disbursed on a chronological basis. Entries include the type of transaction and the amount of monies debited or credited. Transactions include cash received for the payment of vouchers and receipts; these transactions are often listed under the employee who received the transaction. Freight charges are listed under the customer name and include amounts paid and the locations of departure and arrival. Several freight transactions include the name of the railroad used to ship freight. Also included in the cashbook are company expenses such as livery fees, shoeing horses, rider fees, employee wages, advertising, equipment repairs, amounts paid for damages of freight, and items purchased such as horses, wagons, iron safes, and postage.
  - Virginia Express Company Minute Book,1867
    The Virginia Express Company Minute Book, 1867, records the meetings of the company's stockholders and board of directors. These meetings were held early in the life of the Virginia Express Company and detail the organization of the business. The minutes discuss such topics as the election of officers, the fixing of salaries for company directors and employees, and the creation of by-laws for the government of the business. One meeting details which specific railroads the express company would utilize to ship their freight. Also included in the minutes of the first meeting is a list of stockholders that lists each stockholder by name along with the number of shares purchased.
  - Virginia Express Company Minute Book,1868-1869
    Minute Book, 1868-1869, records the meetings of the company's stockholders. Meetings were recorded beginning in December 1868 and end in February 1869 and primarily concern the dissolution of the business and transfer of control to various companies. The minutes include copies of the contracts agreed upon that transferred control of the stage line and railroad shipping ventures. Also included in the minutes are presentations of statements of the assets and liabilities of the company along with a list stockholders. The January 1869 meeting briefly discusses the company's reaction to a robbery that occurred in Norfolk, Virginia.
- John Wayt Invoice Book, 1828-1831, 1 volume
  Historical Information: John Wayt, a son of William Wayt born about 1799, moved to Augusta County, Va., in 1811 where he became a prominent merchant and banker. Wayt was married first to Margaret A. Bell and then to Sarah A. Bell. Wayt died in 1877 leaving behind three children -- Dr. Newton Wayt, J. Howard Wayt, and Mattie Wayt Bledsoe.
  Scope and Content: John Wayt Invoice Book, 1828-1831, chronicles Wayt's purchases that he made most likely for his store. Entries are listed chronologically, and each entry includes date, company and location of purchase, items purchased, and amounts paid. Items purchased included clothing items such as thread, yarn, buttons, silk, flannel, muslin, and lace; food items such as cheese, sugar, coffee, and chocolate; and household items such as knives, bowls, decanters, candlesticks, and soap. Wayt also made several book purchases of dictionaries, almanacs, and primers. Most purchases were made from companies located in either Baltimore, Philadelphia, or Richmond.
  - John Wayt Invoice Book,1828-1831
- William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826 1814-1826, 9 volumes
  Historical Information: William Weaver (1780-1863), born in Flourtown, Pennsylvania, was a prominent and successful ironmaster in Virginia and one of the largest slaveholders in Rockbridge County. During his career, Weaver was involved in a variety of enterprises including merchandising, milling, marble quarrying, and small-scale textile manufacturing, but in July 1814, Weaver made a chance investment in the Virginia iron industry along with his new partner Thomas Mayburry, a Philadelphia merchant whose father and grandfather had been involved in the iron industry in Pennsylvania. Weaver and Mayburry purchased, from William Wilson, Union Forge, located in Rockbridge County, and two blast furnaces, Etna and Retreat, in neighboring Botetourt County along with 6,000 acres of iron ore and woodlands.
  The Retreat and Etna furnace properties were in decline when Weaver and Mayburry made their purchase - Etna Furnace was in serious disrepair while Retreat Furnace possessed inadequate water power. Weaver attempted to put Retreat into blast in 1815, but due to the lack of water, Weaver realized that the furnace at Etna had to be rebuilt. Etna Furnace, originally built in 1792, was situated along Purgatory Creek near Buchanan, Virginia. Weaver succeeded in putting Etna into blast in 1815, thus, insuring that Union Forge would have a steady supply of pig iron.
  Union Forge, renamed as Buffalo Forge, was located on Buffalo Creek in Rockbridge County and would become William Weaver's permanent residence when he relocated to Virginia in 1823. Buffalo Forge was a large complex that had in addition to the forge two water powered mills; a store to sell tobacco, sugar, cloth, and clothing to workers; a shoe and harness shop; carpenter shop; sawmill; and blacksmith. In addition, fields on the furnace properties were used to grow crops of wheat, corn, oats, rye, hay, and clover.
  Initially, William Weaver staffed his furnaces with a mixture of white laborers and hired Black and multiracial enslaved persons, but in October 1815, Weaver purchased eleven enslaved individuals from John Wilson, son of William Wilson from whom he had purchased the furnace properties. Included among these enslaved labaors was Tooler, Black enslaved skilled ironworker. Tooler and this group enslaved laborers formed the basis of Weaver's large crew of skilled ironworkers. Weaver had the bill of sale for these enslaved laborers made out to himself instead of the partnership of Weaver and Mayburry. When the partnership began to dissolve in 1825, Weaver would insist that Mayburry relinquish any claim to any of the enslaved individuals.
  Despite the dissolution of the partnership in 1825, Thomas Mayburry would stay on to operate Etna Furnace. The dissolution of the partnership would ultimately lead to a lengthy chancery suit, primarily pertaining to the ownership rights of the enslaved laborers, that would not be settled until an out-of-court agreement was reached in 1836. A preliminary agreement was reached between the former partners in 1827 when Mayburry agreed to sell Weaver his half of the Union Forge property. After this purchase, Weaver would rename the property Buffalo Forge. Weaver would continue to add to his iron holdings in Virginia, when in 1825, Weaver purchased Lydia Furnace in Rockbridge County. Weaver would later rename this property the Bath Iron Works. Weaver would continue to operate his iron interests until his death on 25 March 1863. Upon his death, Weaver left the Bath Iron Works property to Daniel Brady. The remainder of his property, including Buffalo Forge and many of the skilled enslaved ironworker, passed to his niece Emma Brady, Daniel Brady's wife.
  Today, several buildings still stand at the site of Buffalo Forge, including Weaver's residence, "slave quarters," and several support buildings. The property remains in the hands of the Brady heirs. Some ruins of Etna Furnace exist today on private land, but the remains of Retreat Furnace were destroyed in the 1970s by a treasure hunter searching for the Beale treasure.
  Scope and Content: The William Weaver Business Records, 1814-1826, document Weaver's partnership with Thomas Mayburry and the financial activities of his Virginia iron interests: Etna Furnace, Union Forge (later renamed Buffalo Forge), and Retreat Furnace. The collection consists of the following nine volumes: Etna Furnace Daybook, 1824-1826; Etna Furnace Negro Book, 1815-1822; Etna Furnace Pig Iron Book, 1815-1826; Etna Furnace Pig Iron Book, 1820-1825; Mayburry and Weaver Cashbook, 1818-1826; Retreat Furnace Daybook and Ledger, 1816-1826; Union Forge Daybook, 1819-1824; Union Forge Provision Book, 1818-1826; and William Weaver Invoice Book and Etna Furnace Daybook, 1814-1826.
  Also see: Augusta County Chancery Cause, William Weaver vs.Thomas Mayburry, 1831-019. Avaible Digitially through Chancery Records Index.
  - Etna Furnace Daybook,1824-1826
    Etna Furnace Daybook, 1824-1826, records the daily business transactions of the furnace documenting both expenses and customer orders. Each entry includes the date, type of transaction, and monies credited or debited. Entries for iron purchases include the customer's name along with the amount of iron purchased and monies owed. Expenses for the furnace include freight and shipping fees and the purchase of food, shoes, clothing, and tools. Enslaved laborers are mentioned throughout the daybook with notations concerning the hiring of enslaved persons and paying enslaved persons for overwork. Also recorded are purchases that enslaved workers made at the furnace's store.